Hello friends
I have studied which health insurance companies are best in India for 2025
there are 33 health insurance companies in India
Out of which 28 companies are General insurance but still provides health insurance
remaining 5 companies are exclusive health insurance providers
so I have selected top 10 health insurance companies out of 33
out of which top 4 as per me I am showing in this video
and I am telling reasons for the same
I will show you my study for that
like what is there claim settlement ratio
how many network hospitals they have
what is there solvency ratio
what is there incurred claim ratio
I will try to explain all these technical terms in simple way
then How is there customer support
what are there key features
what are there customer reviews
I have seen many such criteria's for selection
of top health insurance companies
as usual I have prepared simple table
which will explain you all things in single place
as you know I always try to make thigs simpler
so I am Mahesh from TrekBook India
and after working over 30+ years in R&D I resigned early
just to see my beautiful country
So this R&D experience helps me for study
& try to explain you in easy ways
1st column shows health insurance company names
2nd column shows claim settlement ratio
before that RED colur text shows premium collected
3rd column shows network hospotals
then comes solvency ratio
lastly incurred claim ratio
I have studied IRDIA 2024 report
took reference form many other websites
all references are given in the video description
you can study them if you are interested
as usual Green colour shows best companies
out of 33 companies these are best 10
now lets see one by one
first RED arrow shows premiums collected
upto Sept 2024 Star health collected premiums worth 7K crores
highest premium collected in India
so it is top business performer in India (Health insurance)
remember I am talking here for 2024 data
then follows Care health insurance
they have 2.3K crore business
then follows Nivya Bhupa 2.2 K crore
lastly HDFC ergo 1.2Kcrores
so these top 4 are highest business contributors
I try to select highest business companies ..
for the simple reason ...
like why you but highest selling motorcycle since spare part availability is easy
so if you buy highest selling health insurance then ...
they will have high network hospitals
so chance of getting cashless settlement
hospital staff generally aware of process of such companies
ensures smooth and fast processing
for lesser known companies you may face issues for procedures
so I always prioritize high business companies
so ranked 1,2,3,4 accordingly
now lets discuss claim settlement ratios
suppose health insurance company gets 100 claims
and they approve 99 claims
rejected only 1 claim
now there are multiple reasons for rejection
like you gave incorrect info to company
and company knows about that
then claim may get rejected
there can be multiple reasons, I will make separate video for that
now lets get on to point
so that company claim settlement ratio will be 99%
so top 4 highlighted in Green have highest claim settlement ratio
contains star health, care, nivya bhupa, manipal
you can see all companies have claim settlement ratios over 95%
so all these 10 companies are best
out of which I am trying to tell you top 4
the comes network hospitals
as you know network hospitals are important
you have higher chances of cashless claims
star health have 14K network hospitals
hdfc ergo have 12K network hospitals
care health have 11.4K network hospitals
lastly Aditya birla with 11K+
so more green against a company, that is best
now comes solvency ratio
I will try to explain it
you may skip this portion if needed
IRDIA says if you have promised 1000 crores of health insurance
then you need 1.5 times money than promised
in rare case company will be able to pay health insurance amount to all customers at the same time
so min 1.5 is needed
more solvency ratio is good for you
like star health have ratio of 2 means you will get settlement easily in case of any extremes like covid pandemic
so IRDIA has ensured that companies should not reject claims for no money reason
so I have highlighted such companies in Green
then comes ICR Incurred claim ratio
suppose company collects 1K crore premiums
and pays 900 crores of claims
then company makes 100 crore profit
so its 90%
ICR is 90%
so if it is over 90% its good for you but not for company
company may not have enough money in hand for operations
if its too low below 60, you may face issues in claim settlement
I am saying it might happen
so ICR between 70-90% is good
since all 10 companies have more than 60% ICR I have not highlighted cells
so you can easily see best performers
star health have 3 green cells so ranked 1
care health ranks 2
nivya bhupa ranks 3
hdfc ergo ranks 4
now top 2, star health and care health
I have 2 friends representing these companies
in case you need any guidance from them
you will need expert to suggest proper policy considering all things
my friends are IRDIA approved agents
you may fill in form to get help from these friends
instead me answering queries, they can help better
also they can guide when claim arises
so I prefer offline method since online may not help during actual hospitalization process
insurance agents generally  help better way
hence I am doing this as additional help
look at the chart showing premiums collected till Sept 2024
you can get all these charts on reviews.trekbook.in
now lets look at the features
it took me lot of time to study all 10 companies
I have prepared consolidated chart based on study
I will not read through each point
you will get this chart on my website reviews.trekbook.in
link given in video description
read it at your own time
you can ask doubts to me
or my friends can help you too
for sure .. okay
so that's all friends
I have tried to make it simple for you
there are number of complications in selection of health insurance
in my opinion that is second part
first part is company selection
so I have tried my best
if you like do subscribe and share my channel
because I get few subscribers but many questions !!
so I will also be happy with your support
and I will make more such videos for you
thank you so much and bye for now